Guide to the Leigh Hunt Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Leigh Hunt collection
1817-1854
GEN MSS 65
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.2
(1 box)
Letters from Leigh Hunt to various parties, including Charles Ollier; manuscripts by Hunt, including his "Ultra Crepidarius," a satire on William Gifford, which includes a photograph of William Hazlitt.
Hunt, Leigh, 1784-1859
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ongoing collection of documents acquired by gift and purchase from various sources. Type of accession (gift or purchase) and date of acquisition is noted in the box-and-folder list. For further information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
The manuscript, "Ultra Crepidarius" [folder 18] is available on microfilm.
Scope and Contents
This finding aid encompasses accessions of single manuscripts and small groups of manuscripts and other papers, by or pertaining to Leigh Hunt, which the library has chosen to group and list as an artificial collection. Materials incorporated into the collection prior to June 1997 have been organized into 2 series. Series I contains correspondence, while Series II contains manuscripts of assorted writings by Hunt.
Authors, English -- 19th century; Hunt, Leigh, 1784-1859; Ollier, Charles, 1788-1859
- Correspondence, Series I
  - HUNT, LEIGH
    - ALS to William R. Drake, Kensington, [1840] Jul 22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Purchase,, 1949.
    - ALS to William Jerdan, Wimbledon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Gift, 1970.
    - ALS to Douglas William Jerrold, Kensington, London (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Note in third person to Mr. Miller, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      The note directs Mr. Miller to give the Waverly novels to the bearer. It is followed by a list of miscellaneous books.
      Removed from: Oliphant, Margaret. Literary history of England. London, 1882. Ib50 ie882.
    - ALS to Vincent Novello, London, 1817 Oct 15 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - 3 ALS to Charles Ollier, 1843, 1854 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - ALS to [Charles] Ollier, Kensington, 1843 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Purchased, 1944.
    - ALS to J. W. Parker, Jr., Hammersmith, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - ALS to Cyrus Redding, London (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Signed: Henry L. Hunt
    - ALS to [J. G. Vizetelly], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Purchase, 1951.
    - ALS to Benjamin Nottingham Webster, Kensington, London (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Manuscripts, Series II
  - HUNT, LEIGH
    - CORONATION SOLILOQUY OF GEORGE THE FOURTH: autograph manuscript introduction n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Hunt's poem Coronation Soliloquy of His Majesty King George the Fourth was first published in The Examiner, July 29, 1821, but without this introduction which apparently first appeared in his Poems, 1860.
      Gift, 1954.
    - FAITH, HOPE, AND CHARITY; & THE PROSPECTS OF MANKIND: autograph manuscript poem of 12 lines (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - THE FAMILY JOURNAL, NO. V., APRIL FOOLS: autograph manuscript essay, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - LAZY CORNER; OR, BED VERSUS BUSINESS, FROM THE ITALIAN OF BERNI: autograph manuscript, signed., 1845 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      First published in the New Monthly Magazine, October, 1845.
    - PORTRAIT OF HIMSELF FROM ALFIERI: autograph manuscript poem., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
      At head of title: "This poem is in the handwriting of Leigh Hunt. J. T. Fields."
      Portrait of Himself, which is a translation from the Italian of a poem by Vittorio Alfieri, was first published in The Liberal, No. II, 1823.
    - RONDEAU: autograph manuscript poem., [1838?] (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - ULTRA-CREPIDARIUS: autograph manuscript of the satire on William Gifford, with autograph manuscript notes of Hunt's sea voyage to Italy, 1822-23, miscellaneous poems, random jottings for literary projects, and personal memoranda. (Box 1, Folder 18)
      In a blue morocco notebook. 18.5x12cm. 71 p.
      Laid in is a photograph of William Hazlitt, with autograph notes on recto and verso by Alexander Ireland.
      Gift, 1948.